Guide to the Jacques Barzun's Collection of Hector Berlioz Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Jacques Barzun's Collection of Hector Berlioz Records,
1825-1994
Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869.
26.5 linear ft (ca.3l,500 items in 50 boxes, 5 oversize folders, 228 phonograph records, 37 record jackets, 2 record album brochures, & 2 audio tapes in 1 file cabinet).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079190
Biographical Note
French composer.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, papers, essays, etc. relating to Berlioz, and 19th century arts and literature. The correspondence includes original Berlioz letters and over 200 copies of letters relating to Berlioz and the romantic era, written by musicians, critics, historians, and literateurs of the past century. There are many photostats of letters and manuscripts obtained from the principal libraries of the world which hold original Berlioz material. The collection includes much printed material in the form of music scores, published letters, essays, clippings, biographies, music and book catalogues, program notes, and playbills.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Materials Commemorating Berlioz
Series IV: Arranged Correspondence
Series V: Berlioz Societies Records
Series VI: Barzun Notes and Drafts
Series VII: Research Materials
Series VIII: Printed Materials
Series IX: Audiovisual Materials
Series X: Microfilms
Subjects
Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973.; Baillet, Gaston.; Bentley, Eric, 1916-; Berlioz, Harriet Smithson, 1800-1834.; Bizet, Georges, 1838-1875.; Boucher, Anthony, 1911-1968.; Cousins, Norman.; Indy, Vincent d', 1851-1931.; Kahn, Otto Hermann, 1867-1934.; Leinsdorf, Erich, 1912-1993.; Malherbe, Charles.; Marlowe, Julia, 1865-1950.; Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847.; Meyerbeer, Giacomo, 1791-1864.; Parry, C. Hubert H. (Charles Hubert Hastings), 1848-1918.; Prod'homme, J.-G. (Jacques-Gabriel), 1871-1956.; Rolland, Romain, 1866-1944.; Saint-Saëns, Camille, 1835-1921.; Searle, Humphrey.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Starkie, Enid.; Strauss, Richard, 1864-1949.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975.; Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901.; Viardot-García, Pauline, 1821-1910.; Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883.; Weeks, Edward, 1898-1989.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-,--collector.; Barzun, 1881-1973,--collector.; Music--France--19th century.; Arts, French.; Composers--France.; Musicians.; Music critics.; Musicologists.; Announcements.; Audio tapes.; Biographies.; Brochures.; Catalogs.; Essays.; Invitations.; Lists.; Lithographs.; Manuscripts (literary).; Musical scores.; Notes.; Phonograph records.; Photoprints.; Pictures.; Playbills.; Posters.; Programs.; Proofs.; Record jackets.; Collectors.; Composers.; Musicians.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
M76-04 Barzun, Jacques Gift
1991 M-1991 Printed misc. Barzun, Jacques Gift
12/20/93 M-93-12-20 Papers Barzun, Jacques Gift
12/15/94 M-94-12-15 Papers Barzun, Jacques Gift
Alternate Formats
W.H. Auden letters are on microfilm.
LE SONGE D'HʹERODE is on microfilm.
ROMEO ET JULIETTE is on microfilm.
This collection was assembled by Professor Jacques Barzun of Columbia University and by his father, Professor Henri-Martin Barzun. Gift of Jacques Barzun, 1953-1994.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Subseries I.1: Originals by Berlioz
    Original outgoing correspondence of Hector Berlioz, 1838 - 1870. Arranged alphabetically by recepient.
    - Berlioz, Hector to: n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.n.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Berlioz, Hector to "Madame", n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Berlioz, Hector to "Madame", n.p., 27 May n.y., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlin, August 12, n.y., ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Mr", Paris, 12 September 1850, (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Mr.", Dresden, 14 April 1854, ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Mr.", n.p., 1 January 1855, (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Paris], 1 July [1856], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Berlioz, Hector to "Mr", Paris, 21 June 1857, (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: d'Apponyi, Comte, n.p., 26 July n.y., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Benedict, n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Berlioz, Louis], [Paris?], 20, July, n. y., (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Berlioz, Louis], [Paris?], 24 October [1863], (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz, Louis Joseph, Paris, 10 October 1846, ( 3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), [Paris], n.d., (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), [Paris], Oct. 21, [1839], (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), [Paris], Nov. 25, 1843, (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 17)
      [A portion has been cut out from p. 3]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), [Paris], [Nov. 30, 1844], (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), [Lyon], 7 July, 1845, (1p a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Berlioz] Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), Paris, 15 September [c. 1845], (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz Pal, Nanci (Mrs. Camille), [Paris], 31 July1847, (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bowes, M., Paris, 3 December 1839, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bowes, M., Paris, 31 January 1850, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Choudens, Antoine, n.p., n.d., ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Damcke, Berthold, Moscow, [1867], (4 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Danoska, M., [Paris], n.d., (1 p. a.n.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: David, Ferdinand, Hanover, 11 November 1853, (3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Demeur, M., n.p., 8 June [1865], ( 3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Demeur, M., St. Petersburg, [7 February, 1868], (4 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Deschamps, Emile, St. Petersburg, 17 December 1867, ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Director of the Conservatoire, Paris, 6 December, 1855, (3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Dorus-Gras, Madame, [London], November 1847, (3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Dorval, Marie, Paris, 15 October [1833], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Fornier, Estelle, Paris, 19 December 1864, (8 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gras, M., n.p., 5 May, n.y., (1 p. a.n.s., 1p. ) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gras, Madame, n.p., n.d., (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gras, Madame, [Paris], 1843, (2p. a.n.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gras, Madame, n.p., [1851], (1p. a.n.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gye, Frederick, [London?], [July 1853], (2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Haslinger, L., Paris, 11 May 1838, ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Herbeck, Johann von, Paris, 15 March 1867, ( 3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "l'intendant general", Paris, 11 December 1832, (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Jarrett, Henry, [Paris], 5 June 1862, (1 p. a.l.s., 1 envelope, ) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Lamarche, Alfred, n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Lassabathie, M., [Paris], 31 March 1865, (4 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Le Roy, M., n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Leroy, M, n.p., n.d., (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Leroy, M, n.p., Nov. 28, [1810 or 1851?], (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Levy, [Michel-Maurice], [Paris?], [February or Marchc 1845?], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Liszt, Franz ], n.p., 21 December 1830, ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: d'Lostanger, M., n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Mangoldt, Carl Ludwig Armand, Paris, 2 January 1853, ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Monnais, Edouard, n.p., [1852?], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Marmion, Felix ], [Paris], 23 [August 1863], (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Marmion, Felix ], Vienna, [5 September 1867], (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Montalivet, Le Comte de, Paris, 30 March 1835, (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Morel, Auguste, n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: the Musical Society of London, Paris, 23 February 1859, (2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Naudet, M., n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: d'Ortigue, Joseph, London, 5 May [1852], (4 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Camille, [Paris?], [ca. 21 March], n.y., (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Camille, [Paris], 19 March 1838, (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Camille, [Paris], 27 June 1849, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Camille, [Paris], 1 September, 1851, (4p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Camille, [Paris], 2 July 1861, (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Camille, [Paris], 1868, (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Berlioz, Hector; Pal Camille to: Pal, Camille; Berlioz Hector, [Paris], 19 February 1868; [23 February 1868], (1p. a.l.s., 1p. (reply on p. 4 of the letter) a.l., ) (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pal, Mathilde, Paris, 8 April 1868, (2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Panofka, Henri, [Paris], 7 Feb. 1849, (3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: le President de la Section de Musique de L'Institute, Hanover, 10 November, 1853, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Prilleux, M., n.p., n.d., (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ricordi, M., Paris, 1 September 1855, (3 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ricour, M., [Paris], 12 April [1834], ( 2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Rietter, M., Paris, 9 September 1859, (2 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Sainte-Barbe, M., [Paris?], [1833?], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Viardot, Pauline, n.p., 12 Jan. n.y., (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Viardot, Pauline, Flombieres, 29 Jul. [1856], (3p. a.l.s., 1 envelope, ) (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Viardot, Pauline, Paris, [1859], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Viardot, Pauline, n.p., 2 January 1860, (3p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Weil, Heinrich, Paris, 11 May [1841?], (1 p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Subseries I.2: Originals relating to Berlioz
    Original letters from the collection of Jacques Barzun. Most are to Henri-Martin Barzun or Tom S. Wotton, a Berlioz dealer and afficionado. Arranged alphabetically by sender.
    - [Illegible Signature] To: Wotton, Tom S., [Paris], n.d., (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - [Illegible Signature] To: Wotton, Tom S., London, Jun. 16, 1935, (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Andreau, Volkmar To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Zurich, Dec. 10, 1910, (1p a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Association Artistique de Marseille To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Marseille, France, 1910 - 1912, (2 a.l.s. (with envelopes), 2 t.l.s., 1p. (with draft of reply), ) (Box 1, Folder 84 - 85)
    - Association des Concerts Spirituels de la Sorbonne To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Nov. 1-11, 1912, (2 a.l.s. signed by D. Guillaume (incl. envelopes), ) (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Astruc, Gabriel To: Henri Martin Barzun, Paris, Oct. 30, 1912, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Auden, Wysten Hugh To: Jacques Barzun, New York, Oct. 29, 1949, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Auden, Wystan Hugh To: Jacques Barzun, Ischia, Italy, May 3, [1950], (2p. a.ls. (with typsescript copy of reply), ) (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Baggers, Joseph To: Tom S. Wotton, Paris, n.d., (3 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Barry, C.A. To: T.S. Wotton, London, 1885 - 1903, (4 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 91 - 92)
      [Copy of letter from Hans von Bulow missing]
    - Beauclair, Henri To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Dec. 1, 1910; Dec. 31, 1910; Nov. 30 1911, (3 t.l.s (with envelopes), ) (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Bentley, Eric Russell To: Jacques Barzun, Westerly R.I.; New York, 1954 - [1955], (1p. a.l.s. (written on back of an envelope), 1p. t.l., 1p. t.p.c.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 94 - 96)
    - Bibliotheque Nationale To: [Tom. S. Wotton], Paris, 1928 - 1933, (2p. a.l.s. (signature of bibliotheque librarian illegible), 1p. t.l.s. [signed Julien Rain], ) (Box 1, Folder 97 - 98)
    - Bizet, Georges To: Monsieur Baudon, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.l.s. (photostat), ) (Box 1, Folder 99)
      [Photostat, Original in the Wannemacher Collection, Philidelphia]
    - Boschot, Adolphe To: [Henri-Marin Barzun], Paris; Fontenay-sous-bois, 1910 - 1912, (5 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 100 - 102)
    - Bretkopf and Hartel To: C.A. Barry, Bath, Jan. 15, 1901, (2p. t.l.s.(copy, signed by Otto Kling), ) (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Bretkopf and Hartel To: T.S. Wotton, Esq., London, Mar. 12, 1901 - May 26, 1902, (35 a.l.s., 1p., ) (Box 1, Folder 104)
      [Letters from the classicall music publisher ]
    - Bretkopf and Hartel To: Tom S. Wotton, To: Ebenezer Prout, Leipzig, Aug. 29, 1903; Dec. 4, 1903; Jul. 18, 1901, (3 t.l.s., 3p. t.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 105)
      [Illegible signature-- and stamp of Breitkof and Hartel]
    - Brian, Havergal To: T.S. Wotton, Upper Norwood, England, Apr. 17, 1935; [ Apr. 22,] 1935; Jun. 14, 1935; Jun. 25, 1935, (4 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Brough, Fanny To: Tom S. Wotton, [London], Jun. 25, 1896, (8p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - Bruneau, Alfred To: Henri-Martin Barzun; To: Foundation Berlioz, Paris; Niort, France, 1900-1912, (7 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 108 - 111)
    - Brussel, Robert To: Jacques G. Prud'homme, [Paris], 7 July, 1927, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Busby, Thomas R To: T.S. Wotton, London, Apr. 07, 1911, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - Capell, Richard To: Tom S. Wotton, London, Apr. 25, 1935, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 114)
    - Carpenter, Victor To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, (2p. a.l.s. (draft of reply enclosed), ) (Box 1, Folder 115)
    - Chevillard, Camille To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, 1908-1912, (2 a.l.s., 1p. a.l.s. (draft of reply enclosed), ) (Box 1, Folder 116 - 117)
    - Chisholm, Eric To: T.S. Wotton, Glasgow, 1935-1936, (9 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 118 - 120)
    - Clapp. Philip Greeley To: Jacques Barzun, Iowa City, Mar. 13 1946, (5p. survey, 1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 121)
    - Clarke, Mary Cowden To: Hector Berlioz, [London], Sep. 30, 1855, (2p. a.l.s. (photostat), ) (Box 1, Folder 122)
      [Original in Sibley Musical Library, University of Rochester]
    - Colonne, Edouard To: [Tom S. Wotton], Bayswater, [Sep. 1908], (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 123)
    - Colonne, Edouard To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Oct. 23, 1908; Dec. 10, 1910, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 124)
    - Concert Colonne To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Dec. 5, 1910; Dec. 6, 1911, (2 t.l.s. (signed by Petitjeaul, A), ) (Box 1, Folder 125)
    - Concert Colonne To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Dec. 10, 1912, (4p. a.l.s. (signed by Blanquard), ) (Box 1, Folder 126)
    - [Concerts Touche] To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Dec. 10, 1910, (1p. a.n.s. (written on, and in reply to a typed letter from Barzun), ) (Box 1, Folder 127)
    - Conservatoire Nationale du Musique To: Paris, Oct. 7, 1929, (1p. a.l.s (signed by Mathieu), ) (Box 1, Folder 128)
    - Cousins, Norman. To: Jacques Barzun, New York, Apr. 4, 1950, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 129)
    - Derre, E. To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], [Paris], Jan. 30, 1910, (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 1, Folder 130)
    - Dherbecourt (Conseiller Municipal) To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, May 26, 1911; May 31, 1911, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Dirat To: [Foundation Hector Berlioz], Paris, Dec. 16, 1908, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Dobre, Madamoiselle To: Paris, Sep. 2, 1840, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 3)
      [Original in Library of Congress]
    - Drogheda, Charles Garrett Ponsonby Moore, 11th Earl of To Jaques Barzun, Paris, Jun. 20, 1964, (1p. t.l.s. (with copy of eply), ) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Durand et Fils To: Tom. S. Wotton, Paris, Mar. 19, 1905, (4 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 5 - 6)
    - L'Echo de Paris To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Jun. 11, 1913, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ministre de L'Instruction Publique To: Alfred Bruneau, Paris, Dec. 09, 1911, (1p. t.l.s. (signed "pour le ministre, F. Seraut"), ) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Frankenstein, Alfred E. To: T.S. Wotton, San Francisco, Jun. 23, 1936; Jul. 27, 1936; Feb. 1 1937, (3 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Frigara, M. To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], London, Jul. 24, 1910, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Frossard, Emilien E. To: Bishops Lydeard, May 2, 1897, (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Grenoble, Centenaire D'Hector Berlioz To: Tom S. Wotton, Grenoble, Jul. 28, 1903, (1p. a.l.s. (Illegible signature ), ) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hardcastle, C.H. To: [T.S. Wotton], London, Jun. 01, 1917, (4p. a.l.s. 1p. p.s. on card, ) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Hasselmans, Association des Concerts To Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Nov. 09, 1912, (1p. t.l.s. (signed by A. Dandelot, draft of reply enclosed), ) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - d'Hayette, Desire To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], [Lille], [19 Feb. 1910], (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Heymann, G. To: J. Prud'homme, Paris, Dec. 10, 1908, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Holbrooke, Josef To: Tom S. Wotton, Binsbury Park, Oct. 17, 1904, (p.c. ) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - d'Indy, Vincent To: [Tom S. Wotton ?], Paris, Mar. 23, 1910, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Jouve et Cie To: Paris, Aug. 01, 1919, (1p. a.d.s. (Illegible signature), ) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Kahn, Otto Hermann To: Henri-Martin Barzun, New York, Jan. 07, 1919, (t.l.s. 1p., ) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Kerr, F. To: T.S. Wotton, London., n.d., (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Krienitz, Willy To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Munich, Dec. 08, 1910, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - de la Laurencie, L. To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Jan. 18, 1915, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Lamb, Beatrice To: Tom S. Wotton, [London], 1897 - 1901, (2p. t.l.s (with autograph note on verso), 21 receipts for author's fees, ) (Box 2, Folder 24 - 25)
    - Lavaux, Guy To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Sevres, Dec. 14, 1912, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Leinsdorf, Erich To: Jacques Barzub, Larchmont, N.Y., Jan. 02, 1955, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Lewis, James To: [Tom S. Wotton], Bristol; Grenoble, Mar. 17, 1905, (3 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 28 - 30)
    - Cercle Berlioz Lille To: Henri-Martin Barzun; Fondation Berlioz, Lille, Nov. 5, 1909; Dec. 11, 1910, (1p. telegram, 2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 31 - 32)
    - Magnette, Paul To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Leipzig, Dec. 11, 1910, (3p. a.l.s. and an incomplete copy, ) (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Malherbe, Charles To: [Tom S. Wotton], Paris, 1901-1902, (4 a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 34 - 37)
    - Malherbe, Charles To: Henri-Martin Barzun, [n.p.], Feb. 18, 1909, (1p. a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Marix, J. To: [Tom S. Wotton], Paris, 1935-1936, (2 a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 39 - 40)
    - Mendelsohn-Bartholdy, Felix To: Hector Berlioz, Leipzig, Jan. 25, 1843, (4p. a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 41)
      [original in the British Museum]
    - Meurice, Fl. Floment To: [Henri-Martin Berlioz], Paris, Jun. 08, 1911, (1p. a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Meyerbeer [Giacomo] To: Karl Gottlieb Reissiger, n.p., Jan. 24, 1843, (2p. a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 43)
      [with t.s. copy]
    - Morin, Henri A. To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris; Cologne, 1909-1911, (3 a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 44 - 46)
    - Mortin, Joyce and Margaret Gardish To: Tom S. Wotton, Nottingham, Sep. 25, 1937, (2p. a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Mottl, Felix To: [Foundation Hector Berlioz], Munich, Dec. 13, 1908; Dec. 21, 1908, (2 a.l.s. ) (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - [Mottl, Felix] To: Munich, [1909], (calling card with ms note ., ) (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Munich Hoftheater To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Munich, Nov. 02, 1911, (1p. a.l.s., ., ) (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Newman, Ernest To: Tom S. Wotton, London; Hyde Park; Surrey, 1921-1937, (3 t.l.s., 2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 51 - 52)
    - Conseil Municipal Paris To: Le Secretaire General de la Foundation Hector Berlioz, To: Fernaud Chazot, Paris, May 6, 1911; May 27, 1911, (2 t.l.s. (signed by [Zenas], President), ) (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Parry, Hubert H. To: T.S. Wotton, London, Feb. 20, 1915, (4p. a.l.s.., ) (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Probyn, F. To: London, Apr. 05, 1926, (1p. a.l.s.., ) (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Prod'homme, Jacques G. To: [T.S. Wotton], London, Oct. 28, 1928, (1p. a.l.s.., ) (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Prout, Ebenezer To: T.S. Wotton, Hackney, N.E., 1900-1909, (9 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 57 - 59)
    - Radiguer, Henri To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Oct. 29, 1912, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Raphael, Chaim To: Jacques Barzun, New York, Apr. 17, 1957, (1p. t.l.s. (with copy of reply), ) (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Rappard To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, 17 Dec. 1910 - 14 Aug. 1912, (3 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Ricordi, G. To: Tom S. Wotton, Milan, Jan. 07, 1914, (2p. t.l.s. with a.l. music on letter (envelope missing), ) (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Riccou, George To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Dec. 9, 1910; Dec. 5, 1911, (2 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Rocher, F. To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Cote-St.-Andre, 6 Oct. 1919 - 6 Jun. 1916, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Rochette, Ravat (?) To: Madamoiselle Dobre, Paris, May 25, 1842, (2p. a.l.s. (photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 66)
      [original in the Library of Congress]
    - Rolland, Romain To: Henri-Martin Barzun, [Paris]; Zug, Switzerland, 1908-1910, (2 a.n. (on his card, with envelope), 3 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 67 - 69)
    - Ropartz, Guy To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Nancy, Oct. 29, 1912, (2p. a.l.s. (draft of reply enclosed), ) (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Saint-Saens, Camille To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Toulouse, Nov. 18, 1908, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Schloesser, Adolph To: T.S. Wotton, Surrey; Folkstone, 1903 - 1905, (3 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Searle Humphry To: Jacques Barzun, London; Palo Alto, CA., 1955-1965, (1 a.p.c.s., 1p. t.l.s., 1p. a.l.s. (with copy of reply), 1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 73 - 76)
    - Sechiari [Concerts Sechiari] To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Dec. 09, 1910, (2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 77)